Register of the Peng Shu-tse and Zhen Bilan Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Peng Shu-tse and Zhen Bilan papers,
1924-1987
92034
Peng, Shu-tse, 1895-
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, correspondence, theses, and resolutions, relating to the early communist movement in China, and to Trotskyist activities in China and elsewhere. Includes memoirs, other writings, and correspondence of Zhen Bilan, the companion of Peng Shu-tse, relating to the same topics and also to the condition of women in Chinese society.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1992.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Peng Shu-tse [P'eng Shu-chih] and Ch'en Pi-lan [Zhen Bilan]
1895 Peng born, Hunan Province, China
1902 Ch'en born, Hupei Province, China
1920 Peng joined Chinese Communist Party
1921-1924 Peng student at University of Toilers of the East, Moscow
1922 Ch'en joined Chinese Communist Party
1924-1925 Ch'en student at University of Toilers of the East, Moscow
1925 Peng and Ch'en established household
1925-1927 Peng member of national Political Bureau of Chinese Communist Party and editor of Hsiang-tao chou-pao and Hsin ch'ing-nien. Ch'en member of Shanghai Region Political Bureau of Chinese Communist Party and secretary of Shanghai Region Women's Commission
1929 Peng and Ch'en charter members of Chinese Left Opposition. Expelled from Chinese Communist Party
1931 Peng and Ch'en charter members of Communist League of China
1932-1937 Peng imprisoned in Nanking
1948 Peng and Ch'en moved to Hong Kong. Charter members of Revolutionary Communist Party of China
1950 Peng and Ch'en moved to Vietnam
1951 Peng and Ch'en moved to France. Continued as leaders of exiled Chinese section of Fourth International. Peng for many years member of International Executive Committee of Fourth International
1975 Peng and Ch'en moved to United States
1983 Peng died
1987 Ch'en died
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the veteran Chinese Trotskyist leader Peng Shu-tse [P'eng Shu-chih] include also those of his lifelong companion Ch'en Pi-lan [Zhen Bilan]. They date overwhelmingly from the post-1949 period, during which Peng, Ch'en and other Chinese Trotskyists were in exile. Many of their writings deal, however, with their early political activity, and with their participation in the early years of the Chinese Communist Party and especially in the revolutionary events of 1925-1927. The book-length memoirs of Ch'en Pi-lan are particularly notable. They, and others of her writings, are concerned not only with the Chinese revolutionary movement in general, but also with the Chinese women's movement in particular.
Material from the post-1949 period is also of value in documenting activities of the Fourth International and of its exiled Chinese section, and of Trotskyist analysis of the Maoist regime in China, the Chinese commune system, and the Chinese Cultural Revolution. More than half of the material in the collection is in English, but a sizable proportion of it is in Chinese.
The papers were formerly housed in New York City in the Library of Social History, an affiliate of the Socialist Workers Party of the United States. Together with other holdings of the Library of Social History, they were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives from the Anchor Foundation in 1992.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Zhen, Bilan, 1902-1987.; Fourth International.; Communism--China.; Women--China.; Communism.; China.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1973-1987. (Box 1)
  Bibliographies, obituaries, and other biographical data, relating to Peng Shu-tse and Ch'en Pi-lan
  - General. Bibliographies, obituaries, and miscellany, 1977-1987 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Miller, Joseph T., "P'eng Shu-chih and the Chinese Revolution: A Tentative Political Biography," 1973. (Folder 1: 2)
    Typescript
- Speeches and Writings of Peng Shu-tse, 1924-1976. (Box 1-2)
  Arranged chronologically
  - ["The October Revolution and Leninism: For the Commemoration of the Seventh Anniversary of the October Revolution"], Hsiang-tao chou-pao, 1924 November 7. (Folder 1: 3)
    Holograph English translation
  - ["The Historical Significance of the Fighting Period of May 4th Movement in 1919"], 1946 May. (Folder 1: 4)
    Printed copy (in Chinese)
  - ["Le caractère de classe du Parti communiste chinois et du nouveau régime"], 1951 November 8. (Folder 1: 5)
    Typed French translation
  - ["Remarques supplementaires et corrections au 'Rapport sur la question chinois'"], 1952 May 10. (Folder 1: 6)
  - "Criticisms on the Draft Resolution on the Third Chinese Revolution," 1952 June 2. (Folder 1: 7)
  - "An Open Letter to the Central Executive Committee of the Chinese Communist Party: In Protest against Persecutions of Trotskyists in China," 1953 April 14. (Folder 1: 8)
  - "Rise and Decline of Stalinism," 1953 June. (Folder 1: 9)
  - "A Few Criticisms to Serve as Amendments on the Resolution on the Third Chinese Revolution," 1954 March. (Folder 1: 10)
    Holograph
  - "Letter to the Chinese Trotskyist Organization," 1954 April 4. (Folder 1: 11)
  - "A Review on Pabloism: From Pablo to Cochran, Clarke and Mestre," 1955 January 1. (Folder 1: 12)
  - "Resolution on the Parity Commission," 1955 November 7. (Folder 1: 13)
  - "Declaration on the Resolution of Solidarity with the Algerian Struggle for National Liberation," 1956 January 15. (Folder 1: 14)
  - "Draft Resolution on the Evolution of the Post-War International Situation, Its Perspectives and the Tasks of the Fourth International," 1956 December. (Folder 1: 15)
    Mimeograph
  - Article on anniversary of assassination of Leon Trotsky, 1958. (Folder 1: 16)
  - Article on invitation to Nikita Khrushchev to visit the United States, 1959. (Folder 1: 17)
    Holograph (in Chinese)
  - "Are the Communes a 'Superior Type of Economic Organization', or an Effective Instrument for Exploiting and Controlling the Peasants by the CCP?" 1959. (Folder 1: 18)
  - "Communes Are 'Voluntary Peasant Cooperation' and 'Are Administered by Elected Councils Not by Bureaucratic Edict'?" 1959. (Folder 1: 19)
  - "'The Great Productive Increase in Farming' and 'From Enslavement for Women to Equality'," 1959. (Folder 1: 20)
  - "The Criticism of the Several Opinions in Support of the Chinese Rural People's Communes and Our Attitude toward the Chinese Rural People's Communes," 1959. (Folder 1: 21)
  - "A Few More Words on Comrades Liang and Swabeck," 1959 August 18. (Folder 1: 22)
  - "A Supplement to 'The Criticism of the Several Opinions in Support of the Chinese Rural People's Communes and Our Attitude toward the Chinese Rural People's Communes'," 1959 September 15. (Folder 1: 23)
  - Article on situation in France, 1959 December 27. (Folder 1: 24)
  - "On the Nature of the Chinese Communist Party and Its Regime: Political Revolution or Democratic Reform?" 1960 April. (Folder 1: 25)
  - "On the Suggestions and Proposals on the Unity of the World Trotskyist Movement," 1961 May 8. (Folder 1: 26)
  - "My Opinion on the Following Two Questions: The Question of the Cuban Revolution: The Question of China," 1961 June 6. (Folder 1: 27)
  - "A Draft Resolution on the Cuban Revolution and the Task of the Trotskyists," 1961 July 20. (Folder 1: 28)
  - "Where Is Burns Taking the S.L.L.? On the Peril of the Sectarian Tendency of the S.L.L.," 1962. (Folder 1: 29)
  - "Two Extreme Attitudes of the S.L.L. towards the Algerian Struggle of Liberation: From the Policy of Right Adaptation to the Policy of Left Sectarianism," 1963. (Folder 1: 30)
  - "To Continue the Split or to Re-unify the Movement?" 1963 January 14. (Folder 1: 31)
  - "The Evolution of Pabloism and the Struggle against Pabloism by SLL Leaders," 1963 January. (Folder 1: 32)
  - Article upon reading Pravda, 1963 February 22. (Folder 1: 33)
  - Article on Pabloism, ca. 1964. (Folder 1: 34)
  - Article on Chinese Cultural Revolution, 1967. (Folder 1: 35)
  - "The Relationship and Differences between Mao Tse-tung and Liu Shao-chi" [interview with Antonio Farien], 1967 July 6. (Folder 1: 36)
  - Article on Chinese Cultural Revolution, ca. 1968. (Folder 1: 37)
  - "The New Developments in the Chinese Situation," 1969. (Folder 1: 38)
  - ["Maintain the Truth of History, or Fake History?"] 1970 June 28. (Folder 1: 39)
  - Introduction to Leon Trotsky, Problems of the Chinese Revolution [new edition], 1974. (Folder 1: 40)
  - Message to Intercontinental Press banquet [with Ch'en Pi-lan], 1974 April 24. (Folder 1: 41)
  - P'ing Chang Kuo-t'ao ti "Wo ti hui i": Chung-kuo ti erh tz'u ko ming shih pai ti ch'ien yin hou kuo ho chiao hsün [A Criticism of Chang Kuo-t'ao's "My Memoirs": The Course, Consequences and Lessons of the Defeat of the Second Chinese Revolution], 1975. (Folder 1: 42)
  - "Comments on the LTF Draft Resolution 'The Key Issues in the Portuguese Revolution'," 1975 August 1. (Folder 1: 43)
  - "A Statement on the Slanders Circulated by the Healy Group against Hansen, Novack, and the Socialist Workers Party" [with Ch'en Pi-lan and Louis Sinclair], 1976. (Folder 1: 44)
  - ["Questions and Answers on the Civil War in China"], n.d. (Folder 1: 45)
  - Articles on Chinese Cultural Revolution, n.d. (Folder 1: 46)
    Holographs (in Chinese)
  - Notes and fragments (mainly in Chinese), n.d. (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Speeches and Writings of Ch'en Pi-lan, 1933-1981. (Box 2-3)
  - ["The Evolutionist View of Sexual Selection"], Tung-fang tsa-chih, 1933. (Folder 2: 2)
    Printed copy (in Chinese) and typed English translation
  - ["Village Women and the Bankruptcy of Villages"], Tung-fang tsa-chih, 1935. (Folder 2: 3)
    Typed English translation
  - ["The Modern Family Institution and the Question of Children"], Tung-fang tsa-chih, 1935 July-September. (Folder 2: 4)
  - ["Examining the Problem of Women's Suicide"], Tung-fang tsa-chih, 1936. (Folder 2: 5)
  - "Attitude to Life / Attitude à la vie," 1947. (Folder 2: 6)
    Typescript (in English and French)
  - "Looking Back Over My Years with P'eng Shu-tse," 1965 November. (Folder 2: 7)
    Printed copy
  - ["Lies Loving No Facts"], 1968 September 16. (Folder 2: 8)
    Printed copy (in Chinese) and holograph and typed English translations
  - "A Criticism of 'Guerrilla Warfare: Lessons of China'," 1971 January 10. (Folder 2: 9)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "In Memory of My Son, Yau Ming," 1971 May 28. (Folder 2: 10)
  - "A Statement on Portugal," 1975. (Folder 2: 11)
  - "My Experiences on Women's Movement in China," ca. 1970s. (Folder 2: 12)
  - Article on Chinese women's movement, ca. 1970s. (Folder 2: 13)
  - ["My Memoirs"], 1981?
    - Chinese text. (Folder 2: 14-17)
    - English translation. (Box 3)
      - Chapter 1. "Childhood: At Home and at School" (Folder 3: 1)
      - Chapter 2. "Life and Struggles at the College of Education for Women" (Folder 3: 2)
      - Chapter 3. "'Entering the Party' and 'Cancelling the Marriage Agreement'" (Folder 3: 3)
      - Chapter 4. "From Wuhan to Peking" (Folder 3: 4)
      - Chapter 5. "Life and Study in Shanghai" (Folder 3: 5)
      - Chapter 6. "Setback on the Journey to the Soviet Union" (Folder 3: 6)
      - Chapter 7. "To the Soviet Union" (Folder 3: 7)
      - Chapter 8. "Studies and Party Education in the Chinese Section of the Communist University of the Toilers of the East in Moscow" (Folder 3: 8)
      - Chapter 9. "Studies and Party Education in the Chinese Section of the Communist University of the Toilers of the East in Moscow [continued]" (Folder 3: 9)
      - Chapter 10. "The Outbreak of the May 30th Movement and Preparations to Return to China" (Folder 3: 10)
      - Chapter 11. "My Work in Honan, August-October 1925" (Folder 3: 11)
      - Chapter 12. "Work in Shanghai, 1925-1927" (Folder 3: 12)
      - Chapter 13. "A Month in Canton: After Chiang Kai-shek's Coup of March 20, 1926" (Folder 3: 13)
      - Chapter 14. "Back to Shanghai" (Folder 3: 14)
      - Chapter 15. "The Northern Expedition and the Armed Uprising of the Shanghai Workers" (Folder 3: 15)
      - Chapter 16. "The Wuhan Period and the Fifth Congress of the Chinese Communist Party" (Folder 3: 16)
      - Chapter 17. "The Wuhan Government's Liquidation of Communists, and My Life" (Folder 3: 17)
      - Chapter 18. "Two Months in the North" (Folder 3: 18)
      - Chapter 19. "Our Life after Returning to Shanghai from the North, and Chü Ch'iu-pai" (Folder 3: 19)
      - Chapter 20. "The Beginning of Our Life of Hardship" (Folder 3: 20)
      - Chapter 21. "The Beginning of the Chinese Trotskyist Movement and Our Expulsion from the CCP" (Folder 3: 21)
      - Chapter 22. "A Catastrophe Brought on by a Traitor" (Folder 3: 22)
      - Chapter 23. "Peng Shu-chih's Arrest on October 15, 1932" (Folder 3: 23)
      - Chapter 24. "Life during the Five Years Following Shu-chih's Arrest" (Folder 3: 24)
      - Chapter 25. "Life during the Five Years Following Shu-chih's Arrest [continued]" (Folder 3: 25)
      - Chapter 26? "The Socialist Cultural Movement after the Failure of the Revolution, and the Trotskyist Faction" (Folder 3: 26)
      - Chapter 27? "P'eng Shu-chih and Ch'en Tu-hsiu's Release from Prison and their Subsequent Separation" (Folder 3: 27)
      - Chapter 28? "Leaving China: From Hong Kong to Vietnam, 1950" (Folder 3: 28)
  - "A Week in Hospital," n.d. (Folder 3: 29)
- Correspondence, 1952-1981. (Box 4-5)
  Correspondence of Peng Shu-tse and Ch'en Pi-lan, interfiled, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Barbaria, Frank, 1953 (Folder 4: 1)
  - Barnes, Jack, 1971-1976 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Bombaro, Natalie, 1975-1978 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Burton, Robert A., 1966 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Cannon, James P., 1953-1958 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Charlier, Fernand, 1966 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Cornelissen, Igor, 1971-1972 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Dobbs, Farrell, 1958-1960 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Dowson, Ross, 1962-1973 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Evans, Les, 1972-1975 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Feeley, Dianne, 1974 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Fourth International. International Committee, 1957-1958 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Fourth International. International Executive Committee, 1967-1976 (Folder 4: 13)
  - Fourth International. International Secretariat, 1953-1954 (including draft in Chinese) (Folder 4: 14)
  - Fourth International. United Secretariat, 1966-1977 (Folder 4: 15)
  - Frank, Pierre, 1954-1976 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Genecin, Alvin, 1972 (Folder 4: 17)
  - Hamilton, Betty, 1957-1959 (Folder 4: 18)
  - Hansen, Joseph, 1966-1973 (Folder 4: 19)
  - Hansen, Reba, 1966-1969 (Folder 4: 20)
  - Harris, Alan and Connie, 1970 (Folder 4: 21)
  - Healy, Gerry, 1954-1962 (Folder 4: 22)
  - Hillery, Mary, 1973 (Folder 4: 23)
  - Horowitz, Gus, 1972-1973 (Folder 4: 24)
  - Hsin-ch'eng, 1972 (in Chinese) (Folder 4: 25)
  - Institut Léon Trotsky, 1977 (Folder 4: 26)
  - Japan Revolutionary Communist League, 1954-1973 (Folder 4: 27)
  - Jarvis, Helen, 1973 (Folder 4: 28)
  - Jenness, Doug, 1978 (Folder 4: 29)
  - Kagan, Richard C., 1971-1972 (partly in Chinese) (Folder 4: 30)
  - Keil, David, 1967-1979 (Folder 4: 31)
  - Kerry, Karolyn, 1966-1967 (Folder 4: 32)
  - Lee, Shee, 1956-1975 (partly in Chinese) (Folder 4: 33)
  - Lequenne, Michel, n.d. (Folder 4: 34)
  - Lesnik, Rich, 1971-1972 (Folder 4: 35)
  - Mandel, Ernest, 1973-1979 (Folder 4: 36)
  - Mandel, Gisela, 1970-1971 (Folder 4: 37)
  - Meyer, Roger, 1966 (Folder 4: 38)
  - Miller, Joseph T., 1972-1976 (Folder 4: 39)
  - Nabata, Hisashi, 1966-1972 (partly in Chinese) (Folder 4: 40)
  - Nakajima, Mineo, 1969-1971 (Folder 4: 41)
  - Nishi, Kyoji, 1960-1965 (Folder 4: 42)
  - Novack, George, 1952-1973 (Folder 4: 43)
  - Peng family, 1967-1973 (in Chinese) (Folder 4: 44)
  - Petros, n.d. (Folder 4: 45)
  - Pinot, Jean-Christian, n.d. (Folder 4: 46)
  - Polan, Tony, 1970 (Folder 4: 47)
  - Reed, Evelyn, 1953-1963 (Folder 4: 48)
  - Revolutionary Communist Party [China], 1954 (in Chinese with English translation) (Folder 4: 49)
  - Riddell, John, 1970-1972 (Folder 4: 50)
  - Roberts, Demila, 1964-1967 (Folder 4: 51)
  - Sakai, 1973 (Folder 4: 52)
  - Seabold, Mr. and Mrs., 1966-1967 (Folder 4: 53)
  - Sharon, Art, 1966-1967 (Folder 4: 54)
  - Socialist Workers Party [U.S.], 1971 (Folder 4: 55)
  - Stone, Betsey, 1981 (Folder 4: 56)
  - Tam, Jane, 1953-1954 (Folder 4: 57)
  - Tilak, S., 1952-1957 (Folder 4: 58)
  - Unidentified, 1958-1964 (mainly in Chinese) (Folder 4: 59)
  - Vergeat, G., 1970-1973 (Folder 4: 60)
  - Wataru, Yakushiji, 1972-1973 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Waters, Mary-Alice, 1973-1976 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Weissman, George, 1955 (Folder 5: 3)
  - Whitney, W. J., 1962-1963 (Folder 5: 4)
  - Wong, W. H., 1952 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Wu, Chung-hsin, 1973 (in Chinese) (Folder 5: 6)
  - Yamanishi, Eiichi, 1952-1971 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Yin, 1969 (in Chinese) (Folder 5: 8)
- Socialist Workers Party Correspondence, 1953-1981. (Box 5)
  Letters exchanged between members of the Socialist Workers Party (U.S.) relating to Peng Shu-tse and Ch'en Pi-lan, arranged chronologically. Includes discussion of assistance to Peng and Ch'en, their writing projects, and their move to the United States
  - 1953-1974 (Folder 5: 9)
  - 1975 (Folder 5: 10)
  - 1976-1981 (Folder 5: 11)
- Fourth International Subject File, 1930-1975. (Box 5)
  Circulated letters, reports, discussion documents, resolutions, declarations, minutes, and bulletins, relating to political discussions within the Fourth International. Arranged alphabetically by country under discussion
  - General
    - 1953-1955 (Folder 5: 12)
    - 1961-1966 (Folder 5: 13)
    - 1971-1973 (Folder 5: 14)
    - Undated (Folder 5: 15)
  - China
    - 1949-1959 (partly in Chinese). (Folder 5: 16)
      Includes 1953 appeal of Trotskyists in Shanghai
    - 1966-1975 (partly in Chinese). (Folder 5: 17)
      Includes 1972 document in Chinese on Chinese Trotskyist military struggle
    - Undated (Folder 5: 18)
    - Wang, Fan-hsi. Letters, memoirs, and other writings, 1966-1973 (Folder 5: 19)
    - Printed articles from Chinese Trotskyist press, 1955-1967 (in Chinese) (Folder 5: 20)
  - India, 1930-1973 (Folder 5: 21)
  - Japan, 1953-1960 (partly in Chinese) (Folder 5: 22)
  - Sri Lanka, 1954-1967 (Folder 5: 23)